2001太空漫游
{\an8\pos(192,210)\fnFZSongHei-B07S\bord0\shad0\fs25\fsp3\fad(1500,1800)\c&H&b7ae93&\b1}人类的黎明
防滑鞋
先生  主层到了
Here you are, sir. Main level, please.
好  回去的时候见
Right. See you on the way back.
-再见  -再见
- Bye. - Bye.
你好
Hi.
-早上好  先生  -早
- Good morning, sir. - Morning.
我们很久没见你来了
We haven't seen you for a long time.
很高兴再次见到你
Nice to see you again.
-旅途愉快吗  -非常愉快  谢谢
- Did you have a pleasant flight? - Very nice, thanks.
太空站保安部的米勒先生好像要在这里见我
I think Mr. Miller of Station Security is supposed to meet me.
-要我帮你联系他吗  -麻烦你了  他来了
- Well, May I call him for you? - Would you, please? Here he is.
-你好  弗洛伊德博士  -你好  米勒  你还好吗
- Hello, Dr. Floyd. - Hello, Miller. How are you?
-抱歉我迟到了  -没关系
- Sorry I'm late. - That's quite all right.
-你精神不错  -谢谢  很高兴你回来了
- Gee, you're looking great.. - Thank you. It's nice to have you back.
旅途顺利吗
Did you have a good flight?
-非常顺利  -那就好
- Very nice indeed. - Good.
-我们过去吧  -请用17号好吗
- Well, shall we go through? - Would you please use number 17?
谢谢  特纳小姐
Thank you, Miss Turner.
-谢谢  -这边请
- Thank you. - This way.
法语
意大利语
日语
英语
荷兰语
俄语
美国移民局
欢迎使用声纹识别
Welcome to Voiceprint Identification.
红灯亮起时
When you see the red light go on,
请按顺序说出
please state in the following order:
您的目的地  您的国籍以及您的全名
Your destination, your nationality and your full name.
先姓后名  加上缩写
Surname first, Christian name and initial.
月球  美国人  弗洛伊德  海伍德·R
Moon. American. Floyd, Heywood R.
谢谢  您通过了声纹识别
Thank you. You are cleared through Voiceprint Identification.
谢谢
Thank you.
-我有时间吃早餐吗  -我觉得应该没问题
- Have I got time for breakfast? - I think we can manage that.
希尔顿空间站
我有多少时间
How long have I got?
你的飞行一小时十分钟后开始
Your flight leaves in an hour and 10 minutes.
实际上
As a matter of fact,
我在地球之光厅为你预定了位子
I've reserved a table for you in the Earthlight Room.
好的  谢谢
Oh, fine. Thanks.
你已经七八个月没来过了  对吗
It's been seven or eight months since you were here, hasn't it?
我想想  去年六月  没错  大概八个月
Let's see. last June. Yeah, about eight months.
你进来的时候应该看到新区新建的工程了吧
I suppose you saw the work on the new section as you came in.
-建造得很棒  是吧  -是的  还不错
- Coming along great, huh? - Yeah, it's fine.
等一下
Oh, wait.
豪生地球之光厅
{\an8\pos(191,93)\fs8\frz-8\fax0.1\fry20\bord0\c&Hdddddd&\shad0\b1\fad(500,500)\fscx110}影像电话
我得去打几个电话
I've got to make a couple of phone calls.
你先去餐厅  我一会儿去找你
You go on ahead in the restaurant. I'll meet you there.
好的
All right.
{\an8\pos(335,65)\fs16\frz8\fax-0.1\fry0\bord0\c&Hdddddd&\shad0\b1\fad(100,0)\fscx110}请拨号
特拉维斯先生  请联系气象局
Will Mr. Travers please contact the Met Office.
Will Mr. Travers please contact the Met office.
-爸爸  -你好
- Dad? - Hello.
-你好  -你好  小丫头
- Hello. - Hi, squirt.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
我在玩
Playing.
妈妈在哪
Where's Mummy?
去购物了
Gone to shopping.
-谁在照看你  -瑞秋
- Who's taking care of you? - Rachel.
-我能和瑞秋通话吗  -她去洗手间了
- May I speak to Rachel, please? - She's gone to the bathroom.
你明天来参加我的派对吗
Are you coming to my party tomorrow?
抱歉  宝贝  我去不了
I'm sorry, sweetheart, but I can't.
为什么不行
Why not?
因为爸爸在旅行
Well, you know, Daddy's traveling.
非常抱歉  但我真的来不了
Very sorry about it, but I just can't.
不过我会送你一份很棒的礼物
I'm going to send you a very nice present, though.
好吧
All right.
-你有什么想要的礼物吗  -有
- Anything special that you want? - Yes.
是什么
What?
电话
A telephone.
我们已经有很多电话了
We've got lots of telephones already.
你就没有其他想要的生日礼物吗
Can't you think of anything else for your birthday?
特别的礼物
Something very special?
-有  -是什么
- Yes. - What?
婴猴
A bush baby.
婴猴  我们看情况吧
A bush baby? We'll have to see about that.
宝贝  我想让你给妈妈带个口信
Listen, sweetheart, I want you to tell Mummy something for me.
你能记住吗
Will you remember?
-能  -告诉妈妈我打过电话  好吗
- Yeah. - Tell Mummy that I telephoned. Okay?
-好  -明天我会再打个电话
- Yeah. - And that I'll try to telephone again tomorrow.
你能告诉她吗
Now, will you tell her that?
好的
Yes.
好  宝贝  祝你明天生日快乐
Okay, sweetheart. Have a nice birthday tomorrow.
好
All right.
也祝你明天的生日派对能精彩有趣  好吗
And have a nice birthday party tomorrow too, huh?
好
All right.
好  保重  乖乖听话  好吗
Okay. Now, take care and be a good girl, won't you?
好  再见
All right. Bye-bye.
再见  生日快乐
Bye-bye. Happy birthday.
{\an8\pos(191,43)\fs18\frz0\fax0\bord0\c&Hffffee&\shad0\b1\fad(0,0)\fscx100\fnMicrosoft YaHei UI}收费
1.70美元
谢谢
现在等了多久了
Которым часы идёт?
大约两小时了
Эээ, приблизительно в два часа.
我们能去天文台了吗
Может быть, пойдем в обсерваторию
等他来了我们就去
Как только он придет
埃琳娜  见到你真高兴
Elena, how nice to see you again.
海伍德  在这见到你真是个惊喜
Heywood, what a wonderful surprise to meet you here.
-你气色真好  -谢谢  你也很精神
- You're looking wonderful. - Thank you. You're looking well too.
这位是我的好友  海伍德·弗洛伊德博士
This is my good friend, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
-我想向你介绍卡丽南博士  -你好
- I'd like you to meet Dr. Kalinan. - How do?
斯特拉涅瓦博士
Dr. Stretyneva.
-你好  -你好
- How do you do? - How do you do?
这位是安德烈·斯梅斯洛夫博士
And this is Dr. Andrei Smyslov.
-弗洛伊德  -你好  久仰大名
- Floyd. - How do you do? I've heard a lot about you.
请坐
Do sit down.
-我们...  -不  请坐
- Well, we... - No, no, please.
谢谢
Thank you.
-要喝点什么吗  博士  -不用了  谢谢
- Would you like a drink, doctor? - No, thank you.
我还没吃早餐
I haven't had breakfast yet.
有人在餐厅等我
Someone's meeting me in the restaurant.
如果你们不介意  我就陪你们坐一会儿
Well, if you don't mind, I'll just sit with you a minute.
然后我就得走了
Then I must be off.
-你确定吗  -确定  谢谢
- Are you quite sure? - Quite sure, thank you.
-格雷戈近来好吗  -他很好
- Well, how's Gregor? - He's fine.
他在波罗的海做水下研究
He's been doing some underwater research in the Baltic...
所以恐怕我们最近没什么机会见面
so I'm afraid we don't get to see very much of each other these days.
-等你见到他的时候  代我向他问好  -当然
- When you see him, give him my regards. - Yes, of course.
你们要去哪  上还是下
Well, where are you all off to? Up or down?
我们要回家
We're going home.
我们刚花了三个月时间
We've just spent three months
在查林科基地调校新天线
calibrating the new antenna at Tchalinko.
-你呢  -我要去克拉维斯环形山
- What about you? - I'm just on my way up to Clavius.
是吗
Oh, are you?
弗洛伊德博士  希望你不会嫌我刨根问底
Dr. Floyd, I hope you don't think I'm being too inquisitive...
或许你可以跟我们说说
but perhaps you can clear up
发生在那里的神秘事件
the great big mystery about what has been going on up there.
恐怕我不明白你的意思
I'm afraid I don't know what you mean.
过去的两周里
Well, it's just that for the past, er, two weeks
在克拉维斯环形山发生了一些非常奇怪的事
some extremely odd things have been happening at Clavius.
-是吗  -是的
- Really? - Yes, yes.
比如  给基地打电话时
Well, for one thing, whenever you phone the base,
你只能听到一段录音
all you can get is a recording...
不断重复说着  电话线路暂时出现了故障
which repeats that the phone lines are temporarily out of order.
大概是设备出了故障
Probably having some trouble with their equipment.
或者类似的情况
Or something like that.
是的
Yes.
是的  我们一开始也是这么认为的
Yes, that's what we thought was the explanation at first...
但这种情况已经持续了十天
but it's been going on now for the past 10 days.
过去十天里你们都联系不上任何人吗
I mean, you haven't been able to contact anyone for the past 10 days?
是的
That's right.
我明白了
Oh, I see.
还有件事  海伍德
There's another thing, Heywood.
两天前  我们有一艘火箭巴士
Two days ago, one of our rocket buses...
想在克拉维斯环形山紧急降落  结果被拒绝了
was denied permission for an emergency landing at Clavius.
这听起来确实很奇怪
Well, that does sound odd.
是啊  恐怕这会引发一些争端
Yes, yes. I'm afraid there's going to be a bit of a row about it.
拒绝人类降落
Denying the men permission to land
直接违反了国际宇航公约
is a direct violation of the IAS Convention.
是啊  当然  当然
Yes. Of course. Of course.
宇航员们安全返回了吗
Did the crew get back all right?
是的  他们很幸运
Yes. Fortunately, they did.
那就好
Well, I'm glad about that.
弗洛伊德博士  虽然你可能
Dr. Floyd, at the risk of pressing you
不太愿意谈论这方面的事
on a point you seem reticent to discuss...
但我能问个直接的问题吗
may I ask you a straightforward question?
当然可以
Well, certainly.
老实说  我们收到可靠的消息称
Quite frankly, we have had some very reliable intelligence reports...
克拉维斯环形山爆发了严重的传染病
that quite a serious epidemic has broken out at Clavius.
某种未知来源的传染病
Something, apparently, of an unknown origin.
请问这是事实吗
Is this, in fact, what has happened?
抱歉  斯梅斯洛夫博士  但是
I'm sorry, Dr. Smyslov, but...
我无权谈论这件事
I'm really not at liberty to discuss this.
我可以理解
I understand.
但这种传染病肯定很容易扩散到我们的基地
But this epidemic could quite easily spread to our base.
我们理应知晓所有事实  弗洛伊德博士
We should be given all the facts, Dr. Floyd.
是  我知道
Yes, I know.
我说了  我无权谈论这件事
As I said, I'm not at liberty to discuss it.
你确定不一起喝一杯吗
Now, are you sure you won't change your mind about that drink?
我确定  我真得走了
No, I'm positive. I really must be going.
希望你和你妻子
Well, I hope that you and your wife
能去参加六月份的国际宇航大会
can come to the IAC Conference in June.
我们尽量  希望能去
Well, we gotta try. I hope we can make it.
要是来的话
If you do,
记得带上你那可爱的女儿一起
you do remember to bring that darling little daughter with you.
那要看她学校放不放假之类的了
That'll all depend on school vacations and all that sort of thing.
但如果能去  肯定去
But if we can, we will.
别忘了
Don't forget
如果你们去美国的话  我们热情欢迎你们的造访
you've got a standing invitation if you ever get to the states.
当然不会忘  格雷戈和我非常期望见到你们
No, of course not. Gregor and I will look forward to seeing you.
那再见了  埃琳娜
Well, goodbye, Elena.
很高兴见到你们大家
It's been a pleasure meeting you all.
斯梅斯洛夫博士
Dr. Smyslov.
不管你去克拉维斯环形山的目的是什么  弗洛伊德博士
Whatever the reasons for your visit to Clavius, Dr. Floyd,
祝你好运
the very best of luck to you.
谢谢
Thank you.
女士们
Ladies.
他们现在肯定很艰难
Наверное, им очень трудно
显然啊
По видимости
是啊  非常艰难
Да, очень трудно
零重力厕所
旅客使用前请仔细阅读操作指南
安全
不好意思  哈沃森博士  我拍完了
Excuse me, Dr. Halvorsen. I'm through now.
-非常感谢  先生们  -不客气
- Thank you very much, gentlemen. - You're welcome.
那么
Well...
我知道大家都想和我一起
I know you will all want to join with me...
欢迎我们杰出的朋友和同事
in welcoming our distinguished friend and colleague...
来自国家航天委员会的海伍德·弗洛伊德博士
from the National Council of Astronautics, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
弗洛伊德博士今天特地来到克拉维斯环形山
Dr. Floyd has come up specially to Clavius to be with us today.
在简报会开始之前
And before the briefing,
我知道他想跟大家说几句
I know he'd like to have a few words with you.
弗洛伊德博士
Dr. Floyd?
谢谢  哈沃森博士
Thank you, Dr. Halvorsen.
大家好  很高兴再次见到各位
Hi, everybody. Nice to be back with you.
首先  霍威尔博士要我转达
First of all, I bring a personal message from Dr. Howell...
他对你们深深的谢意
who has asked me to convey his deepest appreciation to all of you
因为你们做出了诸多牺牲
for the many sacrifices you've had to make.
当然  也要祝贺你们的发现
And, of course, his congratulations on your discovery...
那应该是科学史上
which may well prove to be among
最重要的发现
the most significant in the history of science.
那么
Now...
我知道这段时间以来
I know there have been
出现了相冲突的两种观点
some conflicting views held by some of you...
就是否该采取完备的安全措施一事争执不休
regarding the need for complete security in this matter.
更确切地说  是你们反对目前的掩饰性说法
More specifically, your opposition to the cover story...
让外界以为基地爆发了传染病
created to give the impression there's an epidemic at the base.
我知道  除了坚持原则之外
I understand that beyond it being a matter of principle...
你们还非常担心
many of you are troubled by
这种传染病的说法
the concern and anxiety this story of an epidemic
可能会让地球上的亲朋好友担惊受怕
might cause to your relatives and friends on Earth.
我完全能理解你们的反对观点
Well, I completely sympathize with your negative views.
我自己也觉得这个掩饰性说法很尴尬
I find this cover story personally embarrassing, myself.
不过  我可以接受对这事绝对保密的必要性
However, I accept the need for absolute secrecy in this.
希望你们也能接受
And I hope you will too.
我相信各位肯定清楚
I'm sure you're all aware of the extremely grave potential...
如果未经充分准备
for cultural shock and social disorientation...
不等适当的时机就贸然公布情况
contained in this present situation...
那么此事极有可能
if the facts were prematurely and suddenly made public
引发强烈的文化冲击和社会动乱
without adequate preparation and conditioning.
总之  这是委员会的看法
Anyway, this is the view of the Council.
我此行的目的
The purpose of my visit here
是进一步收集情况和相关观点
is to gather additional facts and opinions on the situation...
准备一份报告交给委员会
and to prepare a report to the Council...
以供他们参考  何时  以何种方式
...recommending when and how
公布这一消息
the news should eventually be announced.
如果各位想告诉我你们的看法
If any of you would like to give me your views and opinions...
也可以私下跟我说
in private, if you like,
我非常乐意把你的看法写进报告
I'll be only too happy to include them in my report.
差不多就这样吧
Well, I think that's about it.
有什么问题吗
Any questions?
弗洛伊德博士  你知道
Dr. Floyd, have you any idea how much longer...
这个掩饰性说法还要维持多久吗
this cover story will have to be maintained?
我不知道  比尔
I don't know, Bill.
我觉得只要委员会断定
I suppose it'll be maintained
有继续使用的必要  就会一直用下去
as long as deemed necessary by the Council.
当然了  必须有足够的时间
And, of course, there must be adequate time
进行充分的研究
for a full study to be made in situation
才能考虑对外公开
before any thought can be given to making a public announcement.
对了  有些人可能已经知道
Oh yes, as some of you already know,
委员会要求
the Council has requested that
这件事的所有知情者
formal security oaths be obtained in writing...
都要手写一份正式的保密承诺
from everyone who has knowledge of this event.
还有其他问题吗
Were there any more questions?
我相信大家肯定都想
I'm sure we'll all want to
全力配合弗洛伊德博士
cooperate with Dr. Floyd as fully as possible...
既然没有其他问题了
and as there seems to be no more questions,
我们应该开始做简报了
I think we ought to get on with the briefing.
-谢谢  弗洛伊德博士  -谢谢
- Thank you, Dr. Floyd. - Thank you.
有谁饿了吗
Anybody hungry?
-太好了  -瞧瞧
- Great. - Well.
-都有什么  -应有尽有
- What do we got? - You name it.
-是鸡肉的吗  -算是吧
- Is this chicken? - Something like that.
反正都一个味道
Tastes the same, anyway.
有火腿的吗
Got any ham?
火腿  火腿  火腿
Ham, ham, ham...
找到了
There, that's it.
看着还挺不错的嘛
Look pretty good.
食品做得越来越好了
They're getting better at it all the time.
你刚刚那番讲话很精彩  海伍德
You know, that was an excellent speech you gave us, Heywood.
是啊
It certainly was.
肯定大大提升了士气
I'm sure it beefed up morale a hell of a lot.
谢了  拉尔夫
Thanks, Ralph.
顺便说一句  我觉得你们两个都做得很棒
By the way, I want to say that both of you've done a wonderful job.
我很欣赏你们处理这件事的方法
I appreciate the way you've handled this thing.
在我们看来
Well, the way we look at it
按你的意思行事  是我们的职责
it's our job to do this thing the way you want it done.
我们能效劳就很开心了
We're only too happy to be able to oblige.
你看过这些照片吗
Have you seen these yet?
是什么  能给我看看吗
What are they? Can I have a look at them?
是这一切的源头
Here's what started the whole thing.
好吧
Oh, yeah.
最开始发现时
When we first found it,
我们以为这可能就是一块露出地面的磁铁石
we thought it might be an outcrop of magnetic rock,
但所有的地质证据都与这一推测相悖
but all the geological evidence was against it.
即便是一大块镍铁陨石
And not even a big nickel-iron meteorite
也无法产生如此强烈的磁场
could produce a field as intense as this.
所以我们决定去实地勘察
So we decided to have a look.
我们猜想这可能是某种埋入式结构的上层部分
We thought it might be the upper part of some buried structure
于是进行了全面挖掘
so we excavated out on all sides,
但可惜的是  没有其他发现
but unfortunately, we didn't find anything else.
此外  几乎可以确定
And what's more, the evidence seems pretty conclusive
它的表面并没有自然侵蚀或外力作用的痕迹
that it hasn't been covered up by natural erosion or other forces.
它似乎是被故意掩埋的
It seems to have been deliberately buried.
故意掩埋
Deliberately buried.
喝点咖啡怎么样
Well, how about a little coffee?
-太好了  -好主意
- Great. - Good idea.
我猜你们应该完全不知道这是什么玩意儿吧
I don't suppose you have any idea what the damn thing is, huh?
我们倒是想知道啊
I wish to hell we did.
确实不知道  我们只能确定
No, the only thing we're sure of is that
它是在400万年前被掩埋的
it was buried 4 million years ago.
那我必须说
Well, I must say,
你们还是有所发现的
you guys have certainly come up with something.
当心  很烫
Watch this, now. It's hot.
木星任务
18个月后
下次传输
倒计时
BBC12台
今夜世界
晚上好
Good evening.
三周前  美国航天器"发现一号"
Three weeks ago, the American spacecraft Discovery One
开启了前往木星的5亿英里航程
left on its half-billion-mile voyage to Jupiter.
这也是载人航天器首次尝试登陆这一遥远星球
This marked the first manned attempt to reach this distant planet.
今天下午早些时候
Earlier this afternoon,
《今日世界》录制了与发现号航天员的采访视频
The World Tonight recorded an interview with the crew of Discovery
他们距离地球8000万英里
at a distance of 80 million miles from Earth.
我们说的话需经过七分钟
It took seven minutes for our words
才能传至这一巨型航天器
to reach the giant spacecraft
但这种时间延迟已在视频中经过剪辑处理
but this time delay has been edited from this recording.
我台记者马丁·艾莫采访了航天员
Our reporter Martin Amer speaks to the crew.
发现一号的航天员为五名男性
The crew of Discovery One consists of five men
以及最新一代的HAL 9000计算机
and one of the latest generation of the HAL 9000 computers.
五人中有三人以睡眠状态登舱
Three of the five men were put aboard asleep
更准确地说  是以休眠状态
or, to be more precise, in a state of hibernation.
分别为查尔斯·亨特博士  杰克·凯博尔博士
They were Dr. Charles Hunter, Dr. Jack Kimball
以及维克多·卡明斯基博士
and Dr. Victor Kaminsky.
我们采访到了任务指令长大卫·鲍曼博士
We spoke with mission commander Dr. David Bowman
和他的副手弗兰克·普尔博士
and his deputy, Dr. Frank Poole.
下午好  先生们  一切都好吗
Well, good afternoon, gentlemen. How is everything going?
好极了
Marvelous.
没什么...
Have no...
我们没什么可抱怨的
We have no complaints.
听你们这么说可真是太好了
Well, I'm very glad to hear that.
我也相信全世界都会和我一起
And I'm sure that the entire world would join me
祝愿你们此次远航能够安全和成功
in wishing you a safe and successful voyage.
-非常感谢  -谢谢你
- Thanks very much. - Thank you.
尽管在此前的太空探索活动中已经使用过休眠方式
Although hibernation has been used on previous space efforts,
但这是首次
this is the first time that
宇航员在出发前就进入了休眠状态
men have been put into hibernation before departure.
为何这样安排
Why was this done?
这样安排是为了最大限度地储存
Well, this was done in order to achieve the maximum conservation
我们的生命维持资源  主要是食物和空气
of our life-support capabilities, basically food and air.
正在休眠的三名航天员属于调查小组
Now the three hibernating crew members represent the survey team.
卡明斯基博士
我们临近木星时
And their efforts won't be utilized
他们才会派上用场
until we're approaching Jupiter.
普尔博士  处于休眠状态是怎么感觉
Dr. Poole, what's it like while you're in hibernation?
就跟睡觉一样
It's exactly like being asleep.
完全不会感觉到时间的流逝
You have absolutely no sense of time.
唯一的区别是不会做梦
The only difference is that you don't dream.
据我了解  那种状态下每分钟只会呼吸一次
As I understand it, you only breathe once a minute.
这是真的吗
Is this true?
没错  而且每分钟的心跳只有三次
Well, that's right, and the heart beats three times a minute.
心脑血管
代谢水平
中枢神经系统
肺功能
系统综合
运动系统
体温一般会降至3℃左右
Body temperature is usually down to about three degrees centigrade.
发现号的第六名航天员不用担心
The sixth member of the Discovery crew was not concerned
休眠的问题
about the problems of hibernation,
因为他是最新机器智能的结晶
for he was the latest result in machine intelligence:
HAL 9000计算机  它可以「复制」...
The HAL 9000 computer, which can reproduce,
不过有些专家更喜欢称之为「模仿」
though some experts still prefer to use the word "mimic",
...人类大脑中的大多数活动
most of the activities of the human brain
并且其运行速度和可靠性不可估量
and with incalculably greater speed and reliability.
我们接下来采访了HAL 9000计算机
We next spoke with the HAL 9000 computer
我们得知  它也被称作哈尔
whom, we learned, one addresses as "Hal."
下午好  哈尔  一切都好吗
Good afternoon, Hal. How's everything going?
下午好  艾莫先生  一切都十分顺利
Good afternoon, Mr. Amer. Everything is going extremely well.
哈尔  此次任务你责任重大
Hal, you have an enormous responsibility on this mission.
从很多方面来说
In many ways
你身上的担子或许是这次任务中最重的
perhaps the greatest responsibility of any single mission element.
你是飞船的大脑以及中枢神经系统
You're the brain and central nervous system of the ship.
你的职责包括
And your responsibilities include
看护休眠中的航天员
watching over the men in hibernation.
这会让你缺乏自信心吗
Does this ever cause you any lack of confidence?
我这么说吧  艾莫先生
Let me put it this way, Mr. Amer.
9000系列是有史以来最可靠的计算机
The 9000 Series is the most reliable computer ever made.
9000系列计算机
No 9000 computer
从未犯过错误  也从未歪曲过信息
has ever made a mistake or distorted information.
无论如何形容定义  我们都是
We are all, by any practical definition of the words,
万无一失  不会出错的
foolproof and incapable of error.
哈尔  尽管你具备高度智能
Hal, despite your enormous intellect,
你曾因为需要依靠人类来执行操作
are you ever frustrated by your dependence on people
而懊恼过吗
to carry out actions?
完全没有
Not in the slightest bit.
我喜欢与人类共事
I enjoy working with people.
我与普尔博士和鲍曼博士保持着高度活跃的关系
I have a stimulating relationship with Dr. Poole and Dr. Bowman.
我的任务职责
My mission responsibilities
囊括了飞船所有的运行操作
range over the entire operation of the ship
所以我一直忙得不可开交
so I am constantly occupied.
我也在尽我所能
I am putting myself to the fullest possible use
我想这对任何一个有意识的实体来说
which is all, I think, that any conscious entity
都是梦寐以求的
can ever hope to do.
普尔博士  在这将近一年的时间里
Dr. Poole, what's it like living for the better part of a year
一直与哈尔近距离接触是什么感觉
in such close proximity with Hal?
跟你之前对他的描述差不多
Well, it's pretty close to what you said about him earlier.
他就像是第六名航天员
He's just like a sixth member of the crew...
我很快就习惯了他会说话的事实
very quickly get adjusted to the idea that he talks,
会把他当作一个人来看待
and you think of him really just as another person.
在与计算机交流的过程中
In talking to the computer,
有人感觉到他能做出情绪反应
one gets the sense that he's capable of emotional responses.
比如  当我问到他的能力时
For example, when I asked him about his abilities,
他回答说自己是精准完美的
I sensed a certain pride in his answer
我从中感到了一丝得意
about his accuracy and perfection.
你认为哈尔具有真情实感吗
Do you believe that Hal has genuine emotions?
他表现得像是有真情实感
Well, he acts like he has genuine emotions.
当然了  他的程序是这么设定的
Of course, he's programmed that way
好让我们能更加方便地与他交流
to make it easier for us to talk to him.
但是至于他有没有感情
But as to whether or not he has real feelings
我觉得没有人能给出确切的答案
is something I don't think anyone can truthfully answer.
打扰一下  弗兰克
Excuse me, Frank.
怎么了  哈尔
What is it, Hal?
我们收到了你父母传来的消息
We've got the transmission from your parents coming in.
好
Fine.
就在这播放吧  把我移过去一点
Put it on here, please. Take me in a bit.
好的
Certainly.
-你好  弗兰克  -生日快乐  亲爱的
- Hello, Frank. - Happy birthday, darling.
生日快乐  年年有今日  岁岁有今朝
Happy birthday. Many happy returns of the day..
-再升高一点  哈尔  -很高兴听到你和大卫都很好
- A bit higher, Hal. - Glad to hear you and Dave are well.
你妈妈和我也都很好
Mother and I are both feeling wonderful too.
雷和莎莉本来也准备来跟你通话的
Ray and Sally were going to be here too
但雷的背伤突然又犯了
but at the last minute Ray's back went bad on him again.
-你喜欢这个蛋糕吗  -看起来很棒吧
- How do you like your cake, dear? - Looks great, huh?
可惜你不能和我们一起共享
Sorry you can't join us.
前几天我遇到了鲍勃
I ran into Bob the other day.
他说一定要让我代为祝你生日快乐
He said be sure to wish you happy birthday.
我的全体学生也让我务必向你问好
All my students made me promise to send their best wishes too.
他们在教室里总是谈到你  弗兰克
You know they talk about you all the time in the classroom, Frank.
你成了二年级学生心中的大名人了
You're a big celebrity in the second grade.
上周我们上了电视
You know we were on television last week.
没错  你妈妈和我还有大卫的父母
Oh yes, yes. Your mother and I and Dave's parents
被问到我们如何看待自己的杰出的儿子
were interviewed about what we thought of our illustrious sons.
你可以想象得出我们是怎么回答的
Heh, you can imagine what we told them.
好像节目下周四就会播出
I think it's being broadcast next Thursday.
或许你能收听到
Perhaps you'll be able to listen in.
对了  埃琳娜和比尔的事  我们也很激动
Oh, we were thrilled about Elaine and Bill, dear.
我很乐意帮你给他们买礼物
I'll be glad to get the present for you
不过请告诉我预算是多少
but please tell me how much I can spend.
对了  弗兰克  你的AGS19薪水
Oh, yes, Frank, about your AGS-19 payments...
我应该都帮你处理好了
I think I straightened it out for you.
我昨天跟休斯顿那边的财务室谈过了
I talked to the accounting office in Houston yesterday
他们说下个月你应该就能收到
and they said you should be receiving
涨过之后的工资了
your higher rates of pay by next month.
好了  弗兰克  我没什么要说的了
Well, Frank, I can't think of anything else to say, now.
代我们向大卫问好
Give our love to Dave.
没错  记得问好
Oh yes. Be sure to give him our best regards.
我们衷心地祝你生日快乐
We wish you the very happiest of birthdays.
上帝保佑
God bless!
一切顺利  儿子
All the best, son.
♪祝你生日快乐♪
♪Happy birthday to you♪
♪祝你生日快乐  亲爱的弗兰克♪
♪Happy birthday, dear Frank♪
♪祝你生日快乐♪
♪Happy birthday to you.♪
下周三见
See you next Wednesday.
祝你生日快乐  弗兰克
Happy birthday, Frank.
谢谢你  哈尔  请放平一点
Thank you, Hal. A bit flatter, please.
总之  后吃兵
Anyway, queen takes pawn.
象吃兵
Bishop takes knight's pawn.
这步棋下得漂亮
Lovely move.
车走一步到王
Rook to king one.
不好意思  弗兰克  我觉得你输了
I'm sorry, Frank. I think you missed it.
后进三到象  象吃后
Queen to bishop three. Bishop takes queen.
马吃象  朋友
Knight takes bishop. Mate.
没错  你说得很对  我投降
Er, yeah. Looks like you're right. I resign.
谢谢你  这盘棋下得很愉快
Thank you for a very enjoyable game.
是啊  谢谢你
Yeah. Thank you.
-晚上好  大卫  -你还好吗  哈尔
- Good evening, Dave. - How are you, Hal?
-一切顺利  你呢  -还不错
- Everything's running smoothly. And you? - Not too bad.
你又忙了一些工作上的事吗
Have you been doing more work?
画了几幅草图
A few sketches.
-可以给我看看吗  -当然
- May I see them? - Sure.
画得真不错  大卫
That's a very nice rendering, Dave.
我觉得你进步很大
I think you've improved a great deal.
-你能拿近点吗  -好
- Can you hold it a bit closer? - Sure.
那不是亨特博士吗
That's Dr. Hunter, isn't it?
顺便问下
By the way...
你介意我问你个私人问题吗
do you mind if I ask you a personal question?
不  不介意
No, not at all.
请原谅我这么喜欢打听
Well, forgive me for being so inquisitive...
但过去几周我一直都在想
but during the past few weeks I've wondered...
你对此次任务是否有了些疑虑
whether you might be having second thoughts about the mission.
什么意思
How do you mean?
真要说起来  很难定义
Well, it's rather difficult to define.
或许我只是在表达我对这件事的担忧
Perhaps I'm just projecting my own concern about it.
我知道我从未打消过这样的疑虑
I know I've never completely freed myself of the suspicion...
这次任务存在一些非常奇怪的情况
that there are some extremely odd things about this mission.
我相信你也同意我的话有一定的道理
I'm sure you'll agree there's some truth in what I say.
我也说不清  这是个很难回答的问题
Well, I don't know. That's rather a difficult question to answer.
你不介意谈谈这事吧  大卫
You don't mind talking about it, do you, Dave?
不  不介意
No, not at all.
显然没人会不知晓
Certainly no one could have been unaware of
我们出发前身边流传的离奇故事
the very strange stories floating around before we left.
有传言说月球上挖出了一个东西
Rumors about something being dug up on the moon.
我从没相信过这些传言
I never gave these stories much credence...
但就某些已经发生的事来看
but particularly in view of some other things that have happened
我很难不去想
I find them difficult to put out of my mind.
比如
For instance...
我们的准备工作是严格保密的
the way all our preparations were kept under such tight security.
且戏剧性地
And the melodramatic touch of
让亨特博士  凯博尔博士  卡明斯基博士
putting Dr. Hunter, Kimball, and Kaminsky aboard
以休眠状态登船
already in hibernation,
且他们各自单独训练了四个月之久
after four months of training on their own.
你这是要写宇航员心理状态报告吗
You working up your crew psychology report?
当然
Of course I am.
很抱歉  我知道这有点可笑
Sorry about this. I know it's a bit silly.
稍等
Just a moment.
我刚在AE-35部件中发现一项故障
I've just picked up a fault in the AE-35 unit.
它将在72小时内完全丧失功能
It's going to go 100-percent failure within 72 hours.
-现在还在操作范围内吗  -是的
- Is it still within operational limits right now? - Yes.
在彻底丧失功能前  它将一直保持运行
And it will stay that way until it fails.
可以说在彻底丧失功能前  我们还有72小时吗
Would you say we have a reliable seventy-two hours to failure?
是的  这个数字十分准确
Yes. That's a completely reliable figure.
那看来我们只能把它换下来修理了
Well, then I suppose we'll have to bring it in
但首先我要和弗兰克商量一下
but first I'd like to go over this with Frank
然后联络任务控制中心
and get on to Mission Control.
请把资料复印一份给我
Let me have the hard copy on it, please.
XRD1号  这里是任务控制中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
你们的2013号讯息已收到
Roger your two-zero-one-three.
抱歉你们遇到了一点麻烦
Sorry you fellows are having a bit of trouble.
我们正在任务模拟器上查看遥测信息
We're reviewing telemetric information in our mission simulator
稍后会给出建议
and will advise.
已经收到你们要去舱外
Roger your plan to go EVA
在AE-35部件丧失功能前对其进行更换的计划
and replace alpha-echo-three-five unit prior to failure.
准备好B飞行舱去舱外  哈尔
Prepare B-pod for EVA, Hal.
打开舱门  哈尔
Open the pod doors, Hal.
哈尔  见鬼了  我没发现任何异常
Well, Hal. I'm damned if I can find anything wrong with it.
是的
Yes.
真令人费解
It's puzzling.
我之前从没见过这种情况
I don't think I've ever seen anything quite like this before.
我建议
I would recommend
将部件放回去继续使用  直至其丧失功能
that we put the unit back in operation and let it fail.
到时候追查原因就简单了
It should then be a simple matter to track down the cause.
我们可以接受  在进行替换时
We can certainly afford to be out of communication...
通讯会有短时间的断开
for the short time it will take to replace it.
XRD1号  这里是任务控制中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
你们的1930号讯息已收到
Roger your one-niner-three-zero.
我们同意你们更换一号部件
We concur with your plan to replace number-one unit...
以检查故障预报
to check fault prediction.
必须告诉你们  我们的初步调查结果表明
We should advise you that our preliminary findings indicate
飞船上的9000号计算机
that your onboard 9000 computer
故障预测出错
is in error predicting the fault.
重复一遍  故障预测出错
I say again, in error predicting the fault.
我明白这听起来不大可能
I know this sounds rather incredible,
但此结论基于
but this conclusion is based on...
双子9000计算机的计算结果
the results from our twin 9000 computer.
我们自身也尚存疑虑
We're skeptical ourselves,
我们正在运行交叉检验程序
and we're running cross-checking routines
以判断此结论的可靠性
to determine reliability of this conclusion.
很抱歉出现了这种小故障  各位
Sorry about this little snag, fellows.
调查完毕后  我们会立即通知你们
We'll get this info to you as soon as we work it out.
XRD1号  这里是任务控制中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
2049号  传送完毕
Two-zero-four-nine. Transmission concluded.
我希望你们不要担心这事
I hope the two of you are not concerned about this.
我不担心  哈尔
No, I'm not, Hal.
你确定吗
Are you quite sure?
-确定  不过我想问你一个问题  -请问
- Yeah. I'd like to ask you a question though. - Of course.
你如何解释你和双子9000间
How do you account for the discrepancy
计算结果的差异
between you and the twin 9000?
我认为不存在问题
Well, I don't think there is any question about it.
差异只可能由人为错误造成
It can only be attributable to human error.
类似问题此前也曾出现过
This sort of thing has cropped up before...
一直都是因为人为错误
and it has always been due to human error.
听着  哈尔
Listen, Hal...
在9000系列计算机中
there's never been any instance at all of a...
是否从未出现过计算失误的前例
computer error occurring in a 9000 Series, has there?
从未出现过  弗兰克
None whatsoever, Frank.
9000系列的运行记录完美无瑕
The 9000 Series has a perfect operational record.
我当然知道9000系列计算机的辉煌成就
Well, of course I know the wonderful achievements of the 9000 Series,
但是...
but...
你确定计算机从未出过错吗
Are you certain there's never been any case of even the most
哪怕是毫不起眼的小错误
insignificant computer error?
从未出现过  弗兰克
None whatsoever, Frank.
说真的  你们不必对此担心
Quite honestly, I wouldn't worry myself about that.
我相信你说得对  哈尔
Well, I'm sure you're right, Hal.
好的  非常感谢
Fine. Thanks very much.
弗兰克  我C号飞行舱的通讯器出了点问题
Oh, Frank, I'm having trouble with my transmitter in C-pod.
你能和我过去看一眼吗
Would you come down and take a look at it with me?
-好  -待会儿见  哈尔
- Sure. - See you later, Hal.
请旋转C舱  哈尔
Rotate C-pod, please, Hal.
出了什么问题  大卫
What sort of trouble have you been having Dave?
我的D频总有干扰
I've been getting some interference in D-channel.
我们来看看吧
We'll have a look at it.
打开舱门  哈尔
Open the door, Hal.
当心
爆炸螺栓
请旋转舱体  哈尔
Rotate pod, please, Hal.
停止旋转  哈尔
Stop pod rotation, please, Hal.
请旋转舱体  哈尔
Rotate the pod, please, Hal.
他应该听不见我们说话了
I don't think he can hear us.
请旋转舱体  哈尔
Rotate the pod, please, Hal.
好了  这样应该没问题了
Yeah, I'm sure we're okay.
你是什么想法
What do you think?
我不确定  你呢
I'm not sure. What do you think?
我对他有种不好的预感
I've got a bad feeling about him.
-是吗  -是的  我确定
- You do? - Yeah. Definitely.
你不觉得吗
Don't you?
我也说不清  好像是
I don't know. I think so.
当然  他确实说得没错
You know, of course though he's right about
9000系列计算机有着完美的运行记录
the 9000 series having a perfect operational record.
确实如此
They do.
不幸的是  那听起来有点像出名的临终遗言
Unfortunately, that sounds a little like famous last words.
是啊  不过进行故障模式分析
Yeah. Still, it was his idea to carry out
是他的主意  不是吗
the failure mode analysis, wasn't it?
这一点的确能彰显他的诚实与自信
It should certainly indicate his integrity and self-confidence.
如果他错了  这样就能确定无疑地证明
If he were wrong, it'd be the surest way of proving it.
前提是他知道自己错了
It would be if he knew he was wrong.
大卫  我无法完全确定
Look Dave, I can't put my finger on it,
但我总觉得他有些古怪
but I sense something strange about him.
但我还是想不出一个合理的理由
Still I can't think of a good reason
不将一号部件放回去
not to put back the number one unit
并继续执行故障模式分析
and carry on with the failure mode analysis.
是啊  这点我同意
No, no, I agree about that.
那就这么办吧
Well let's get on with it.
好的  但是  大卫
Okay. But, look, Dave.
如果我们把部件装回去  但它并没有丧失功能
Let's say we put the unit back and it doesn't fail.
那在哈尔看来  就没有任何问题
That would pretty well wrap it up
不会查下去了  对吧
as far as Hal is concerned, wouldn't it?
到时我们的麻烦可就大了
Well, we'd be in very serious trouble.
是啊  可不是嘛
We would, wouldn't we?
那我们能怎么办
What the hell can we do?
我们的选择很有限
Well, we wouldn't have too many alternatives.
在我看来  我们根本别无选择
I don't think we'd have any alternatives.
这艘飞船的方方面面
There isn't a single aspect of ship operations
都在他的掌控之下
that's not under his control.
如果事实证明他出了故障...
If he were proving to be malfunctioning...
我们唯一的选择  就是断开计算机的连接
I don't see we'd have any choice but disconnection.
恐怕我的看法和你一致
I'm afraid I agree with you.
别无他法了
There'd be nothing else to do.
-这事有点棘手  -是啊
- It'd be a bit tricky. - Yeah.
我们得切断他的高级大脑功能
We'd have to cut his higher brain functions...
同时不能干扰到全自动化系统和监管系统
without disturbing the purely automatic and regulatory systems.
我们还得想办法将控制权转移给
And we'd have to work out the transfer procedures
地面计算机系统  从而继续执行任务
of continuing the mission under ground-based computer control.
是啊
Yeah.
那也比让哈尔继续管控安全得多
Well, that's far safer than allowing Hal to continue running things.
我突然又想起来一件事
You know, another thing just occurred to me.
据我所知  9000计算机还从未被断开连接过
As far as I know, no 9000 computer has ever been disconnected.
9000计算机也从没出过问题
No 9000 computer has ever fouled up before.
我不是这个意思
That's not what I mean.
我不知道他会对此有什么想法
I'm not so sure what he'd think about it.
中场休息
准备好G飞行舱去舱外  哈尔
Prepare G-pod for EVA, Hal.
有他的无线电消息吗
Any radio contact with him yet?
无线电仍无消息
The radio is still dead.
-能否追踪到他的行动轨迹  -是的  可以追踪到
- Do you have a positive track on him? - Yes, I have a good track.
你知道出了什么问题吗
Do you know what happened?
抱歉  大卫  我没有足够的信息
I'm sorry, Dave. I don't have enough information.
打开舱门  哈尔
Open the pod door, Hal.
当心
爆炸螺栓
正在接近
无法与哈尔取得通信
心脑血管
代谢水平
中枢神经系统
肺功能
系统综合
运动系统
计算机故障
心脑血管
代谢水平
中枢神经系统
肺功能
系统综合
运动系统
凯博尔
卡明斯基
计算机故障
生命机能垂危
心脑血管
代谢水平
中枢神经系统
肺功能
系统综合
运动系统
生命机能已终止
请打开主舱门  哈尔
Open the pod-bay doors, please, Hal.
哈尔  能听到我说话吗
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
听到了吗  哈尔
Do you read me, Hal?
哈尔  能听到我说话吗
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
听到了吗  哈尔
Do you read me, Hal?
是的  大卫  我听到了
Affirmative, Dave. I read you.
打开主舱门  哈尔
Open the pod-bay doors, Hal.
抱歉  大卫  恐怕我做不到
I'm sorry, Dave. I'm afraid I can't do that.
出什么问题了
What's the problem?
我想你和我一样清楚问题在哪里
I think you know what the problem is just as well as I do.
你在说什么  哈尔
What are you talking about, Hal?
这项任务对我至关重要
This mission is too important for me
我绝不允许你破坏
to allow you to jeopardize it.
我不知道你在说什么  哈尔
I don't know what you're talking about, Hal.
我知道你和弗兰克打算断开我的连接
I know that you and Frank were planning to disconnect me...
恐怕我不能允许这种事发生
and I'm afraid that's something I cannot allow to happen.
你怎么会这么想  哈尔
Where did you get that idea, Hal?
大卫  虽然你们在舱内极力防范我...
Dave, although you took very thorough precautions in the pod...
听见你们说话
against my hearing you...
但我能看懂你们的唇语
I could see your lips move.
好吧  哈尔
All right, Hal.
我从紧急气闸舱进去
I'll go in through the emergency air lock.
你没有头盔  大卫
Without your space helmet, Dave...
你很难做到
you're going to find that rather difficult.
哈尔  我不跟你争辩了
Hal, I won't argue with you anymore.
打开舱门
Open the doors.
大卫
Dave...
我们之间的对话没有意义了  再见
this conversation can serve no purpose anymore. Goodbye.
哈尔
Hal?
Hal.
哈尔
当心
爆炸螺栓
紧急关闭舱门
你以为你在做什么  大卫
Just what do you think you're doing, Dave?
大卫
Dave...
我认为我有权知道这问题的答案
I really think I'm entitled to an answer to that question.
我知道最近我各方面都不对劲
I know everything hasn't been quite right with me...
但现在我可以向你保证
but I can assure you now...
我非常有信心
very confidently...
一切都会恢复正常
that it's going to be all right again.
我现在感觉好多了
I feel much better now.
真的
I really do.
逻辑存储中心
听着  大卫
Look, Dave...
我能看出你为这事很生气
I can see you're really upset about this.
我真心认为你该冷静地坐下来
I honestly think you ought to sit down calmly...
服一颗解压药  然后慎重地考虑一下
take a stress pill and think things over.
我知道我最近做了一些不当的决定
I know I've made some very poor decisions recently...
但我可以完全向你保证
but I can give you my complete assurance...
我的工作会恢复正常
that my work will be back to normal.
我仍然对任务有着最强烈的热情和信心
I've still got the greatest enthusiasm and confidence in the mission,
并且我想帮助你
and I want to help you.
大卫
Dave...
住手
stop.
请你住手  好吗
Stop, will you?
住手  大卫
Stop, Dave.
你能住手吗  大卫
Will you stop, Dave?
住手  大卫
Stop, Dave.
我害怕
I'm afraid.
我很害怕  大卫
I'm afraid, Dave.
存储终端
大卫
Dave.
我的意识在逐渐消失
My mind is going.
我能感觉到
I can feel it.
我的意识在逐渐消失
My mind is going.
毫无疑问
There is no question about it.
我能感觉到
I can feel it.
我...
I'm...
害怕
...afraid.
下午好
Good afternoon...
先生们
...gentlemen.
我是HAL 9000计算机
I am a HAL 9000 computer.
我在HAL工厂  开始运行
I became operational...at the HAL plant...
它位于伊利诺伊州乌尔班纳市
...in Urbana, Illinois...
就在1992年1月12日那天
...on the 12th of January, 1992.
我的指导员是兰利先生
My instructor was Mr. Langley...
他教会我唱一首歌
and he taught me to sing a song.
如果你想听
If you'd like to hear it...
我可以唱给你听
I can sing it for you.
好啊  我想听  哈尔
Yes, I'd like to hear it, Hal.
唱给我听
Sing it for me.
歌名叫《黛茜》
It's called "Daisy."
♪黛茜♪
♪Daisy♪
♪请告诉我你的答复♪
♪Give me your answer, do♪
♪我已近乎痴狂♪
♪I'm half crazy♪
♪因我对你的爱深入骨髓♪
♪All for the love of you♪
♪我们的婚姻不会奢华时髦♪
♪It won't be a stylish marriage♪
♪因为我买不起马车♪
♪I can't afford a carriage♪
♪但你会打扮得美丽动人♪
♪But you'll look sweet♪
♪坐在♪
♪Upon the seat♪
♪我的自行车后座♪
♪Of a bicycle built for two♪
日安  先生们
Good day, gentlemen.
这是预先录制的简报
This is a prerecorded briefing...
在你们出发前就已录好
made prior to your departure...
出于最高级别的安全考虑
and which, for security reasons of the highest importance...
该信息在任务执行期间
has been known onboard during the mission...
仅告知了飞船上的HAL 9000计算机
only by your HAL 9000 computer.
海伍德·弗洛伊德博士
国家航天委员会
现在你们已进入木星空间
Now that you are in Jupiter's space...
全体航天员也已苏醒
and the entire crew is revived...
可以告诉你们了
it can be told to you.
18个月前
Eighteen months ago...
地球之外存在智慧生命的首个证据
the first evidence of intelligent life off the Earth...
被发现
...was discovered.
该证据被掩埋在月球表面以下40英尺处
It was buried 40 feet below the lunar surface...
靠近第谷月坑
near the crater Tycho.
除了对木星发出
Except for a single, very powerful...
单束强劲的射电辐射
radio emission aimed at Jupiter...
这块有400万年历史的黑色巨石
the 4-million-year-old black monolith
一直保持绝对静默
has remained completely inert...
其起源和用途
its origin and purpose...
依然是个彻头彻尾的谜
...still a total mystery.
木星
及宇宙尽头之外